I have a studio in Berlin --
لدي أستديو في برلين--
let me cue on here --
أسمحوا لي بالإشارة على هذا --
which is down there in this snow, just last weekend.
الذي هو هناك في الثلج، في نهاية الأسبوع الماضي.
In the studio we do a lot of experiments.
نقوم بالكثير من التجارب في الأستديو.
I would consider the studio more like a laboratory.
أعتبر الأستديو أشبه بالمختبر.
I have occasional meetings with scientists.
لدي إجتماعات عرضية مع العلماء.
And I have an academy, a part of the University of Fine Arts in Berlin.
ولدي أكاديمية، جزء من جامعة الفنون الجملية في برلين.
We have an annual gathering of people,
لدينا مناسبة سنوية تجمع الناس،
and that is called Life in Space.
ويسمى ذلك بالحياة في المكان
Life in Space is really not necessarily about
الحياة في المكان ليس بالضرورة حول
how we do things, but why we do things.
كيف نفعل الأشياء، بل لماذا نفعل الأشياء.
Do you mind looking, with me, at that little cross in the center there?
هلّا نظرتم معي، في ذلك الرمز في المنتصف هناك؟
So just keep looking. Don't mind me.
إذاً واصلوا التمعن. لا تأبهوا بي.
So you will have a yellow circle, and we will do an after-image experiment.
إذاً ستشاهدون دائرة صفراء. وسنقوم بتجربة ما بعد الصورة.
When the circle goes away you will have another color, the complementary color.
عندما تختفي الدائرة سيكون هناك لون آخر، اللون التكميلي.
I am saying something. And your eyes and your brain are saying something back.
أنا أقول شيئاً. وعيونكم وعقولكم تقول شيئاً كاستجابة.
This whole idea of sharing, the idea of constituting reality
الفكرة الكاملة للتشارك، الفكرة في تشكّل واقع
by overlapping what I say and what you say --
عن طريق التداخل بين ما أقول وما تقولون --
think of a movie.
فكروا بهذا كـ فيلم.
Since two years now, with some stipends from the science ministry in Berlin,
منذ عامين حتى الآن، مع بعض الرواتب من وزارة العلوم في برلين،
I've been working on these films
كنت أعمل على هذه الأفلام
where we produce the film together.
حيث ننتج الأفلام سوياً.
I don't necessarily think the film is so interesting.
لا أعتبر الفيلم ممتع جداً بالضرورة.
Obviously this is not interesting at all in the sense of the narrative.
ومن الطبيعي أن هذا ليس ممتعاً بالمرة في سياق السرد.
But nevertheless, what the potential is --
ولكن مع ذلك، القابلية هي --
and just keep looking there --
وواصلوا التحديث هناك --
what the potential is, obviously,
القابلية هي، بالطبع،
is to kind of move the border of who is the author,
هي نوع من تحريك الحدود لمن هو المؤلف،
and who is the receiver.
ومن هو المتلقي.
Who is the consumer, if you want,
من هو المستهلك، اذا شئتم،
and who has responsibility for what one sees?
ومن لديه المسئولية تجاه ما يراه الشخص؟
I think there is a socializing dimension
أعتقد أن هناك بُعد في التنشئة الإجتماعية
in, kind of, moving that border.
في، نوع من، تحريك تلك الحدود.
Who decides what reality is?
من يقرر ما هو الواقع؟
This is the Tate Modern in London.
هذا هو تيت العصري في لندن.
The show was, in a sense, about that.
كان العرض، بمعنى ما، حول ذلك الموضوع.
It was about a space in which I put half a semi-circular yellow disk.
كان حول المكان الذي أضع فيه قرص أصفر نصف دائري.
I also put a mirror in the ceiling, and some fog, some haze.
وأضع أيضاً مرآة في السقف، وبعض الضباب.
And my idea was to make the space tangible.
وكانت فكرتي أن نجعل الفراغ ملموساً .
With such a big space, the problem is
مع هذه المساحة الكبيرة، المشكلة هي
obviously that there is a discrepancy
بالطبع أن هناك تباين
between what your body can embrace,
بين ما تستطيع أجسادنا أن تمثله
and what the space, in that sense, is.
وبين المكان ، بذلك المعنى.
So here I had the hope that by inserting some natural elements,
إذاً فقد كان لدي أمل أنه و بإضافة بعض العناصر الطبيعية،
if you want -- some fog -- I could make the space tangible.
اذا شئتم، بعض الضباب، أقدر على جعل المكان محسوساً.
And what happens is that people, they start to see themselves in this space.
وما يحدث هو أن أؤلئك الناس، بدأوا رؤية أنفسهم في ذلك المكان.
So look at this. Look at the girl.
إذاً أنظروا لهذا. أنظروا للفتاة.
Of course they have to look through a bloody camera
بالطبع ينبغي عليهم النظر عبر كاميرا دموية
in a museum. Right? That's how museums are working today.
في المتحف. صحيح؟ هكذا تعمل المتاحف اليوم.
But look at her face there,
لكن أنظروا لوجهها هناك،
as she's checking out, looking at herself in the mirror.
وبينما تحدق النظر، تنظر لنفسها في المرآة.
"Oh! That was my foot there!"
"أوه! أنه قدمي هناك!"
She wasn't really sure whether she was seeing herself or not.
لم تكن متأكدة بالفعل من أنها ترى نفسها أم لا.
And in that whole idea,
و السؤال هو:
how do we configure the relationship between our body and the space?
كيف نتعرف على العلاقة بين أجسامنا والمكان ؟
How do we reconfigure it?
كيف نعيد تعريف العلاقة؟
How do we know that being in a space makes a difference?
كيف نتعرف على أنه بمجرد التواجد في المكان يحدث فرقاً؟
Do you see when I said in the beginning, it's about
هل تلاحظون عندما قلت في البداية، أن الأمر حول ذلك
why, rather than how?
لماذا، بدلاً عن الآن؟
The why meant really,
وماذا يعني حقاً،
"What consequences does it have when I take a step?"
" ما هي التبعات الملازمة لها عندما أخذ خطوة؟"
"What does it matter?"
" ما هي الأهمية ؟"
"Does it matter if I am in the world or not?"
" هل يهم اذا كنت في العالم أم لا؟"
"And does it matter whether the kind of actions I take
" وهل يهم سواء كان نوع الأفعال التي أقوم بها
filter into a sense of responsibility?"
تترجم الى نوع من المسئولية؟"
Is art about that?
هل الفن يدور حول ذلك؟
I would say yes. It is obviously about
سأقول نعم. أنه بالطبع
not just about decorating the world, and making it look even better,
ليس فقط تزيين العالم، وجعله يبدو أفضل.
or even worse, if you ask me.
أو حتى أسوأ، اذا سألتوني
It's obviously also about taking responsibility,
من الواضح أيضاً أنه عن تحمّل المسئولية،
like I did here when throwing some green dye in the river
مثل ما فعلت هنا برشق بعض الصبغة الخضراء على النهر
in L.A., Stockholm, Norway and Tokyo,
في لوس أنجلوس، أستكهولم، النرويج وطوكيو،
among other places.
بين أماكن أخرى.
The green dye is not environmentally dangerous,
الصبغة الخضراء ليست خطرة على البيئة،
but it obviously looks really rather frightening.
ولكن من الواضح أنها تبدو مفزعة حقا.
And it's on the other side also, I think, quite beautiful,
وهي على الجانب الآخر أيضاً، كما أعتقد، جميلة جداً.
as it somehow shows the turbulence in these kind of downtown areas,
على نحو ما يظهر الاضطراب في هذا النوع من مناطق وسط المدينة،
in these different places of the world.
في هذه الأماكن المختلفة من العالم.
The "Green river," as a kind of activist idea, not a part of an exhibition,
النهر الأخضر، هي نوع من أفكار الناشطين، ليست جزء من معرض،
it was really about showing people,
أنها في الحقيقة حول إقناع الناس،
in this city, as they walk by,
في المدينة، التي يعيشون فيها،
that space has dimensions. A space has time.
أن لذلك المكان أبعاد. مكان لديه زمن.
And the water flows through the city with time.
ويتدفق الماء عبر المدينة مع مرور الوقت.
The water has an ability to make
لدى الماء المقدرة على جعل
the city negotiable, tangible.
المدينة قابلة للتفاوض، ملموسة.
Negotiable meaning that it makes a difference
قابلة للتفاوض تعني أن هناك فرقاً
whether you do something or not.
سواء فعلت شيئاً أم لم تفعل.
It makes a difference whether you say, "I'm a part of this city.
سيحدث فرقاً سواء قلت، "أنا جزء من هذه المدينة.
And if I vote it makes a difference.
واذا قمت بالتصويت سيحدث فرقاً.
If I take a stand, it makes a difference."
اذا أتخذت موقفاً، سيحدث فرقاً."
This whole idea of a city not being a picture is,
الفكرة الرئيسية للمدينة ليست كونها صورة،
I think, something that art, in a sense,
أعتقد، أن الفن شئ، بمعنى ما،
always was working with.
كان دائماً مصاحب له.
The idea that art can actually evaluate the relationship
الفكرة أن الفن يمكن أن يقيّم العلاقة
between what it means to be in a picture,
بين المعنى أن تكون في صورة،
and what it means to be in a space. What is the difference?
والمعنى أن تكون في فراغ. ما هو الفرق؟
The difference between thinking and doing.
الفرق بين التفكير والفعل.
So these are different experiments with that. I won't go into them.
لذا فهذه تجارب مختلفة لذلك. لن أدخل في تفاصيلهم.
Iceland, lower right corner, my favorite place.
آيسلندا، أسف الركن على اليمين، أفضل الأمكنة لي.
These kinds of experiments, they filter into architectural models.
هذه الانواع من التجارب، ترشح في نماذج معمارية.
These are ongoing experiments.
أنها تجارب مستمرة.
One is an experiment I did for BMW,
أحدها تجربة قمت بها ل BMW ،
an attempt to make a car.
محاولة لصنع سيارة.
It's made out of ice.
مصنوعة من الثلج.
A crystalline stackable principle in the center on the top,
مبدأ تكويم الكريستال في أعلى المركز،
which I am trying to turn into a concert hall in Iceland.
التي أحاول تحويلها الى قاعة إحتفالات في آيسلندا.
A sort of a run track, or a walk track,
وهناك نوع من مسار تشغيل ، أو جسر للمشاة ،
on the top of a museum in Denmark,
على قمة متحف في الدنمارك،
which is made of colored glass, going all around.
تم صنعه من الزجاج الملون، يغطي كل المساحة.
So the movement with your legs
إذاً الحركة بقدميك
will change the color of your horizon.
ستغيّر لون الأفق.
And two summers ago at the Hyde Park in London,
وقبل صيفين، في حديقة هايد بارك في لندن،
with the Serpentine Gallery:
مع معرض أفعواني :
a kind of a temporal pavilion where
نوع من سرادق الزمانية حيث
moving was the only way you could see the pavilion.
كانت الحركة هي الطريق الوحيد يمكّنك من رؤية الأفق.
This summer, in New York:
هذا الصيف، في نيويورك:
there is one thing about falling water which is very much about
هناك شئ واحد عن تساقط المياة الذي هو غالباً حول
the time it takes for water to fall.
الزمن المطلوب لتسقط المياة.
It's quite simple and fundamental.
أنه بسيط للغاية وأساسي.
I've walked a lot in the mountains in Iceland.
لقد تنقلت كثيراً في الجبال في آيسلندا.
And as you come to a new valley,
وكلما تأتي الى وادي جديد،
as you come to a new landscape, you have a certain view.
كلما وصلت الى مشهد جديد، تحصل على منظر معين.
If you stand still, the landscape
اذا توقفت، المشهد
doesn't necessarily tell you how big it is.
لا يخبرك بالضرورة كم هو كبير.
It doesn't really tell you what you're looking at.
لا يخبرك في الواقع ما الذي تنظر إليه.
The moment you start to move, the mountain starts to move.
في اللحظة التي تبدأ الحركة، يبدأ الجبل في الحركة.
The big mountains far away, they move less.
الجبال الكبيرة البعيدة، تتحرك قليلاً.
The small mountains in the foreground, they move more.
الجبال الصغيرة في المقدمة، يتحركون أكثر.
And if you stop again, you wonder,
واذا توقفت مجدداً، تتعجب،
"Is that a one-hour valley?
" هل هذا وادي يُقطع في ساعة؟
Or is that a three-hour hike, or is that a whole day I'm looking at?"
أم أن ذلك تسلق يستغرق ثلاث ساعات، أم أن هذا ما أنظر إليه طوال اليوم؟"
If you have a waterfall in there,
اذا كان لديك شلال هناك،
right out there at the horizon; you look at the waterfall
هناك بالضبط في الأفق. تنظر ناحية الشلال
and you go, "Oh, the water is falling really slowly."
وتقول، "أوه، المياة تسقط ببطء شديد."
And you go, "My god it's really far away and it's a giant waterfall."
وتقول، " يا إلهي أنه بعيد حقاً وهو شلال ضخم."
If a waterfall is falling faster,
اذا كانت المياة تسقط بصورة أسرع
it's a smaller waterfall which is closer by --
فهو شلال أصغر وأقرب --
because the speed of falling water is pretty constant everywhere.
لأن سرعة التساقط ثابتة في كل مكان.
And your body somehow knows that.
وجسمك بطريقة ما يعرف ذلك.
So this means a waterfall is a way of measuring space.
إذاً هذا يعني أن الشلال هو طريقة لقياس المكان .
Of course being an iconic city like New York,
بالطبع أن تكون مدينة رمزية مثل نيويورك،
that has had an interest in somehow
لذلك مصلحة بطريقة ما
playing around with the sense of space, you could say that New York
في اللعب مع نوع من المكان ، يمكن القول أن نيويورك
wants to seem as big as possible.
تريد أن تبدو كأكبر ما يمكن.
Adding a measurement
إضافة مقياس
to that is interesting:
لذلك شئ مثير:
the falling water suddenly gives you a sense
فجأة تعطيك المياة المتساقطة معنى
of, "Oh, Brooklyn is exactly this much --
ل ، " أوه، بروكلين بالضبط بهذا الحجم --
the distance between Brooklyn and Manhattan, in this case
المسافة بين بروكلين ومانهاتن، في هذه الحالة
the lower East River is this big."
إن أسفل النهر الشرقي كبير."
So it was not just necessarily about putting nature into the cities.
إذاً فأن الأمر لم يكن بالضرورة عن وضع الطبيعة في المدن.
It was also about giving the city a sense of dimension.
لقد كانت أيضاً حول تزويد المدينة بنوع من الأبعاد.
And why would we want to do that?
ولماذا نريد أن نفعل ذلك؟
Because I think it makes a difference
لأنني أعتقد أنها ستحدث فرقاً
whether you have a body
سواء كان لديك جسم
that feels a part of a space,
يحس بكونه جزء من مكان
rather than having a body which is just in front of a picture.
بدلاً عن أن لديك جسم يقف فقط أمام صورة.
And "Ha-ha, there is a picture and here is I. And what does it matter?"
و " ها-ها، هناك صورة وها أنا ذا. وما هو الفرق؟"
Is there a sense of consequences?
هل هناك معنى للتبعات؟
So if I have a sense of the space,
واذا كان لدي شعور بالمكان،
if I feel that the space is tangible,
إذا شعرت أن المكان ملموساً،
if I feel there is time,
إذا شعرت أن هناك زمن،
if there is a dimension I could call time,
إذا كان هناك بُعد يمكن أن أسميه الزمن،
I also feel that I can change the space.
أشعر أيضاً أنني أستطيع تغيير المكان .
And suddenly it makes a difference
وفجأة تحدث فرقاً
in terms of making space accessible.
بالنسبة لجعل المكان يمكن الوصول إليه.
One could say this is about
قد يقول أحد أن هذا حول
community, collectivity.
المجتمع، جماعياً.
It's about being together.
الأمر حول البقاء معاً.
How do we create public space?
كيف يمكننا إبداع فراغ عام؟
What does the word "public" mean today anyway?
على أي حال، ما الذي تعنيه كلمة "عام" هذه الأيام ؟
So, asked in that way,
إذاً، السؤال بتلك الطريقة،
I think it raises great things about
أعتقد أنها تبرز أشياء عظيمة حول
parliamentary ideas, democracy, public space,
أفكار البرلمان، الديموقراطية، المساحة العامة،
being together, being individual.
البقاء معاً، التفرّد.
How do we create
كيف نبدع
an idea which is both tolerant to individuality,
فكرة مسامحة مع الفردانية،
and also to collectivity,
وأيضاً جماعية،
without polarizing the two
بدون إستقطاب الأثنين
into two different opposites?
الى نقيضين مختلفين؟
Of course the political agendas in the world
بالطبع الأجندات السياسية في العالم
has been very obsessed, polarizing the two against each other
ظلت مهووسة جداً، بإستقطاب الأثنين ضد بعضهما البعض
into different, very normative ideas.
الى فوارق، وأفكار معيارية جداً.
I would claim that art and culture,
سأدّعي أن الفن والثقافة،
and this is why art and culture are so incredibly interesting
وهذا هو السبب في أن الفن والثقافة مثيران للإهتمام بشكل لا يصدق
in the times we're living in now,
في الأوقات التي نعيشها الآن،
have proven that one can
قد أثبتوا أن الشخص يستطيع
create a kind of a space
إبداع نوع من المكان
which is both sensitive to individuality
الذي هو حساس تجاه الأثنين الفردانية
and to collectivity.
والجماعية.
It's very much about this causality, consequences.
الأمر متعلق بشدة حول هذه العلاقة بين المسببات والتبعات.
It's very much about the way we link
الأمر متعلق أكثر بالطريقة التي نربط بها
thinking and doing.
التفكير والأفعال.
So what is between thinking and doing?
إذاً ما العلاقة بين التفكير والأفعال؟
And right in-between thinking and doing,
وهناك بين التفكير والأفعال،
I would say, there is experience.
أقول، هناك خبرة.
And experience is not just
والخبرة ليس فقط
a kind of entertainment in a non-casual way.
نوع من الترفيه بطريقة غير مُحالة.
Experience is about responsibility.
الخبرة تتعلق بالمسئولية.
Having an experience is taking part in the world.
أن يكون لديك خبرة هو أن تأخذ دور في العالم.
Taking part in the world is really about sharing responsibility.
أخذ دور في العالم هو في الحقيقة متعلق بتقاسم المسئولية.
So art, in that sense,
إذاً الفن، بمعنى من المعاني،
I think holds an incredible relevance
أعتقد يحمل أهمية لا تُصدّق
in the world in which we're moving into,
في العالم الذي نتحرك تجاهه.
particularly right now.
تحديداً الآن.
That's all I have. Thank you very much.
هذا كل ما لدي. شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)